Finding Aid for NAMI Michigan records, 1977-2011
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
NAMI Michigan records 1977-2011 1980s-1990s
NAMI Michigan.
9813 Aa 2
The National Alliance for the Mentally Ill is a grassroots support and advocacy group for the mentally ill and their families. This record group focuses on the Michigan chapters of NAMI Lansing and NAMI Michigan. Records in this collection include annual reports, bylaws, meeting minutes and agendas, correspondence, event materials, educational and advocacy program materials, brochures, newspapers, newsletters, resource guides, and various other printed materials.
5 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
This record group was donated by NAMI Michigan (donor no. 8745 ) in August 1998 The bulk of the record group was donated on February 8, 2012. Additional materials were received on June 5, 2012.
Periodic additions to the records are expected.
The record group is open to research.
The National Alliance for the Mentally Ill (NAMI) was founded in April of 1979. It comprised of various support groups for parents of adults with mental illness. NAMI soon developed into having many affiliated groups within communities around the United States. In 1999, those groups changed their names to NAMI in order to become a nationally recognized organization. Now it is the nation's largest grassroots mental health organization that exists, not only for parents of adults with mental illness, but also for families, friends, individuals, and business that have come together to provide support, education, and advocacy for all who have been affected by mental illness.
In 1974 the Oasis Fellowship (now NAMI Lansing) was formed in Lansing, Michigan in order to assist with housing arrangements for the mentally ill leaving state hospitals. It was also one of the first groups for family members, not just parents, of persons with mental illness. Since then, the organization has evolved into the "Tri-county's Voice on Mental Illness," and has expanded their mission to "improve the lives of those who suffer from neurobiological brain disorders and their families through support, education, advocacy, and research" (NAMI Lansing Mission Statement, 2012).
By January 1986, many more mental illness support and advocacy groups had developed and banded together to form NAMI Michigan. Their mission is to work at the state level to "improve the quality of life for persons, families and others, who are affected by mental illness, including children with serious emotional disorders, through support, education, advocacy and research"(NAMI Michigan Mission Statement, 2012).
The records of NAMI Michigan and NAMI Lansing document the dedicated efforts of the groups in providing support, education, advocacy, and research for the mentally ill and their families. The primary focus of their work has evolved into building a community for all those affected by mental illness. The series in the record group are: Administrative Files, Correspondence, Events, Programs, Publications/Printed Materials, and Miscellaneous.
Subjects:
Mentally ill--Michigan.; Mentally ill--Michigan--Lansing.; State Alliance for the Mentally Ill of Michigan.; Alliance for the Mentally Ill of Michigan.; NAMI Lansing.; NAMI Michigan.; Oasis Fellowship.
- Administrative Files
  The Administrative Files consist of annual reports, by-laws, meeting agendas and minutes, and various other documents from the Alliance for the Mentally Ill of Michigan, NAMI Lansing, NAMI Michigan, and the State Alliance for the Mentally Ill. It also includes various administrative documents and correspondence pertaining to other related mental illness support and advocacy groups.
  - Alliance for the Mentally Ill of Michigan (AMIM)
    - Annual Reports 1989-1996 (Box 1)
    - Bylaws and Consumer and Family Expectations 1991-1998 (Box 1)
    - Meetings
      - Board of Directors
        - 1990-1993 (Box 1)
        - 1994-1995 (Box 1)
        - 1996-1997 (Box 1)
        - 1998-2002 (Box 1)
      - Forensics Committee 1977, 1989-1994 (Box 1)
      - Membership -- General and Annual 1989-2002 scattered (Box 1)
      - Public Policy 1991-2002 (Box 1)
  - Alliance for the Mentally Ill of Greater Lansing, OASIS Fellowship, Inc. (AMI-OASIS)
    (also known as NAMI Lansing, Inc.)
    - Applications for Funding 2011 (Box 1)
    - Articles of Incorporation 1978-2010 scattered (Box 1)
    - Bylaws 1987-2011 (Box 1)
    - Legal Documents 1978-2011 scattered (Box 1)
    - Meetings
      - 1982-1989 (Box 1)
      - 1990-1991 (Box 1)
      - 1992-1993 (Box 1)
      - 1994-1995, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - 1996-1998 (Box 1)
      - 1998-2000 (Box 1)
      - 2000-2001 (Box 2)
      - 2001-2003 (Box 2)
      - 2003-2005 (Box 2)
      - 2005-2007 (Box 2)
      - 2007-2009 (Box 2)
      - 2009-2011 (Box 2)
    - Standards of Excellence September 2009 (Box 2)
  - National Alliance for the Mentally Ill of Michigan (NAMI Michigan)
    - Annual Reports 2006 (Box 2)
    - Bylaws 2001, 2009 (Box 2)
    - Meetings
      - Board of Directors, Minutes
        (contents of folders in reverse chronological order)
        - 2001-2005 (Box 2)
        - 2006-2007 (Box 2)
        - 2007-2008 (Box 2)
        - 2008-2010 (Box 2)
        - Extra Minutes and Miscellaneous 1990-2010 scattered (Box 2)
      - Public Policy 2001 (Box 2)
    - President -- Huebl, Hubert C. 2002-2003 (Box 2)
  - State Alliance for the Mentally Ill (SAMI)
    - Annual Reports 1988-1989 (Box 2)
    - Board Meetings
      - 1985-1987 (Box 2)
      - 1988-1990 (Box 2)
    - Bylaws 1987-1990 (Box 2)
      (includes 1990 Position Statements)
    - History and Chronology 1979-1988 (Box 2)
    - Originals and Copies of Originals 1988 (Box 2)
    - Regionalizing 1995-1996 (Box 2)
  - Related Mental Illness Support and Advocacy Groups
    - AMI of Mid-Michigan 1988-1991 (Box 2)
    - AMIM -- Oakland County 1988-1989, 1997 (Box 2)
    - Alzheimer's Disease and Related Disorders Association (ADRDA) -- Greater Ann Arbor Chapter 1987 (Box 2)
    - Coldwater Regional Mental Health Center Citizens' Advisory Council 1988, 1990 (Box 2)
    - Community Advocating for a Reasonable Environment (CARE) 1986 (Box 2)
    - Community Mental Health Board (CMH) -- Community Support Services (CSS) (Box 3)
      - General 1982-1996, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - CMH Reports 1988-1995 scattered, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Department of Mental Health Action Committee for Women (ACW) 1989-1990 (Box 3)
    - Greater Lansing Area Dual Recovery Work Group November 1993, February 1996 (Box 3)
    - Macomb County Community Mental Health Board 1995-1996 (Box 3)
    - Michigan Association of Community Mental Health 1998-1999, 2010 (Box 3)
    - Michigan Department of Mental Health (DMH) -- Mental Health Advisory Council
      - General 1985-1995 scattered (Box 3)
      - Annual Reports 1987-1989 (Box 3)
    - Michigan Protection and Advocacy Service (MPAS) 1985-1986 (Box 3)
    - NAMI Washtenaw County
      (previously known as AMI of Washtenaw County (WAMI) and Friends for Mental Health)
      - Annual Reports 1997-2000 (Box 3)
      - Board Meetings 1984-2009 scattered (Box 3)
      - Bylaws 2000 (Box 3)
      - History and Fact Sheets 1994-2008 (Box 3)
    - Schizophrenics Anonymous 1992 (Box 3)
    - Tourette Syndrome Association -- Michigan Regional Chapters 1979-1996 scattered (Box 3)
- Correspondence
  The Correspondence are comprised of letters, documents, and miscellaneous papers collected by Arlie Kinnee (Forensic Committee Chair, AMIM), Norma Prouty (AMI Education sub-committee), and Betty Smith (AMI OASIS Liaison with the Community Mental Health Board). This series highlights their individual involvement in NAMI and various other mental illness groups. Also included in this series are correspondence and miscellaneous documents pertaining to AMIM collected by Embert and Kalinich (no other names or titles given).
  - AMIM -- Collected by Embert and Kalinich 1991-1995 (Box 3)
    (no other names or titles given)
  - Kinnee, Arlie (Forensic Committee Chair, AMIM) February 1993, November 1993 (Box 3)
  - Prouty, Norma (AMI Education sub-committee) 1979-2005 scattered, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Rees, Carol (NAMI Board member)
    - General 1986-2005 scattered (Box 3)
    - Letters to the Editor 1988-1998 scattered (Box 3)
  - Smith, Betty, (AMI OASIS Liaison with CMH) 1987-1992 scattered (Box 3)
- Events
  The Events series includes brochures, flyers, schedules, programs, and various other materials from forums, conferences, and conventions pertaining to mental illness in the state of Michigan.
  - AMIM Annual Statewide Conference 1990-1995, 2000 (Box 3)
  - AMI OASIS Public Forums 1987-1997 (Box 3)
  - Awareness Week 1987-1997 scattered (Box 3)
  - Family Focus Group on Valued Outcomes of Psychosocial Programs conducted by Esther Onaga 1995 (Box 3)
  - Michigan Department of Mental Health/Department of Social Services/ Michigan Coalition Against Domestic Violence Statewide Conference Proceedings December, 1987 (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous 1989-2008 scattered (Box 4)
  - Northern Michigan Regional Alliance for the Mentally Ill Conference 1995-1996 (Box 4)
  - SAMI Annual Conference 1987-1990 (Box 4)
- Programs
  The Programs series has materials from projects, training, and educational programs that focus on providing support for those with mental illness.
  - Managing Persons with Mental Disabilities 1991-1993, 1999, 2001, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Managing Persons with Mental Disabilities: A Curriculum Guide for Police Trainers, 1989 (Box 4)
  - Michigan Self-Help Clearinghouse: A Program of Michigan Protection and Advocacy Service 1994 (Box 4)
  - My Sister's Sister-- A professional play to promote the understanding of mental illness, 1999 (Box 4)
  - Supported Employment Technical Assistance Project, Employment Training Specialist Series -- Follow Along Services Participant Manual November 1987 (Box 4)
- Publications/Printed Materials
  The Publications/Printed Materials include brochures, flyers, mailers, news releases, newspapers, and newsletters from various mental illness support and advocacy groups from around Michigan. The proposals and reports in this series mainly revolve around preventing violence towards the mentally ill, especially mentally ill women. This series also includes a number of resource guides for families dealing with mental illness.
  - Brochures (Box 4)
  - Flyers, Mailers, and News Releases 1988-2006 scattered (Box 4)
  - Newsletters
    - Editing the AMI Newsletter by Harriet Shetler, 1980s-1990s (Box 4)
    - The Advocate, 1984-2001 scattered (Box 4)
    - AMIM Leadership Update, 1993-1994, 1998-1999 (Box 4)
    - AMIM News, 1995-2000 (Box 4)
    - AMI of Oakland County -- The Bulletin Board, 2000-2001 (Box 4)
    - AMI Reflections
      (newsletter title changed multiple times)
      - State Alliance for The Mentally Ill of Michigan Newsletter, 1986-1989 (Box 4)
      - AMI Reflections: State Alliance for The Mentally Ill of Michigan, 1989-1990 (Box 4)
      - AMI Reflections: Alliance for the Mentally Ill of Michigan, 1990-1993 (Box 4)
    - Connections: Newsletter of NAMI Washtenaw County, 1992-2012 scattered (Box 4)
      (earlier issues titled Connections: Newsletter of the Alliance for the Mentally Ill of Washtenaw County)
    - MPAS Exchange, 1990-2004 scattered (Box 4)
    - NAMI Messenger: The Tri-County's Voice on Mental Illness
      (earlier issues titled AMI Messenger)
      - 1995-2005 (Box 4)
      - 2006-2011 (Box 4)
    - NAMI Michigan News from around the state, 2002-2008 (Box 5)
    - Newsletter: Alliance for the Mentally Ill of Jackson-Hillsdale County, January-July 1996 scattered (Box 5)
    - Oakland AMI Update
      (earlier issues titled Alliance for the Mentally Ill of Michigan -- Oakland County Monthly Newsletter)
      - 1988-1991 (Box 5)
      - 1992-2002 (Box 5)
    - Rose Hill Update, 1991-1995 scattered (Box 5)
      (includes a brochure for the Rose Hill Center)
    - Update, 1983-1998 (Box 5)
      (earlier issues titled OASIS Update)
    - Update From the Mental Health and Aging Education Consortium: A Project of the Center for Aging Education at Lansing Community College (Box 5)
      (earlier issues titled Update on Aging Education), 1990-1991 and 1995
    - Miscellaneous 1984-2002 scattered (Box 5)
  - Newspapers 1989-2000s (Box 5)
  - Proposals and Reports
    - Creating a Caring Circle of Community Support -- The Wrap-Around Service Model: Greater Lansing Mental Health Task Force Report, 1993 (Box 5)
    - A Decade of Progress, circa 1991 (Box 5)
    - A Proposal for Client Service Management for Oakland County, March 1994 (Box 5)
    - Proposal for Enhanced Family Education Services, 1995 (Box 5)
    - A Report on A Survey of Community mental Health Boards for FY 90-91, March 1993 (Box 5)
    - Report from the Special Joint Legislative Committee on Spouse Abuse, 1978 (Box 5)
    - Treatment of Women by the CMH System: A Proposal for Change, October 1986 (Box 5)
    - Working Against Violence (Second Edition) -- A Bibliography: A Listing of the Domestic Violence Prevention and Treatment Board, Michigan Office of Children and Youth Services Resource Library Collection, 1990 (Box 5)
  - Resource Guides 1989-2005 scattered (Box 5)
- Miscellaneous
  The Miscellaneous series includes awards and recognitions, a photograph, and documentation pertaining to Senate Bill 525.
  - Awards and Recognitions 1988-2000 scattered
    (includes nomination letters)
    - General (Box 5)
    - Hill, Donald and Helen (Box 5)
    - Nominations (Box 5)
    - Rees, Carol and Jerry (Box 5)
  - Photographs (Box 5)
  - Senate Bill 525 1995
    - AMIM 1995 Legislative Committee, May-November 1995 (Box 5)
    - Mental Health Code Workgroup on Accreditation and Credentialing Michigan Health and Hospital Association June-September, 1995 (Box 5)
    - Reports and Memoranda 1993-1995, 2 folders (Box 5)